<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-10T21:33:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Galaxy Science to Data Science</title><subtitle>My personal website.</subtitle><author><name>Matt Stevans</name><email>stevans@utexas.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Adding inline footnotes in HTML and CSS</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/inline-footnotes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding inline footnotes in HTML and CSS" /><published>2020-08-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/inline-footnotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/inline-footnotes/">&lt;p class=&quot;notice--success&quot;&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;#just-the-code&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to jump to the section with the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoy reading the blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/&quot;&gt;FiveThirtyEight&lt;/a&gt; for the data-driven reporting on politics, sports, and life. It is also the first place I recall encountering the inline footnotes some time in 2017. I remember being way too impressed when I clicked on a footnote, the remaining article text lowered creating a blank space, and the footnote appeared out of thin air. Now that I have my own blog, I want to give my reads the same pleasurable experience. Since I don’t know JavaScript, which 538 uses for their inline footnotes, my goal is to use HTML and CSS. In this post, I share what I’ve found for others who want to do something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fivethirtyeights-inline-footnotes&quot;&gt;FiveThirtyEight’s Inline Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FiveThirtyEight inline footnote feature allows a reader to view a footnote immediately after the footnote number by clicking on the footnote number. The reader can then hide the inline footnote by clicking on the “x” which appears in place of the clicked footnote number or continue scrolling through the text without hiding the footnote. Here is a GIF demonstarting how a reader can toggle a footnote in a 538 &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-does-an-0-7-start-tell-you-about-an-nfl-coach/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/inline-footnotes/538-inline-footnote.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image-center&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is an elegant way to include extra details for the interested reader without requiring the efficient reader to be distracted from the main idea of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To replicate this on my own blog, I did what most people do–I Googled it. I found the basic HTML and CSS code I needed from the user Unrelated’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/40336366/in-line-footnotes-with-only-html-css-in-notes/40391190#40391190&quot;&gt;answer&lt;/a&gt; to the question “In-line footnotes with only HTML/CSS (in-notes?)” on Stack Overflow. To mimic the style of the feature on FiveThirtyEight I added some lines in the CSS to adjust the formating. Here is a GIF of how it looks on my blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/inline-footnotes/my-blog-inline-footnote.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image-center&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the following footnote to try it for yourself. &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cb2&quot; /&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;cb2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the footnote text.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; This sentence (and the rest of the article) will move a few lines down. You can click the footnote number again to hide the footnote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-code&quot;&gt;The Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a template of the HTML code to insert within the text where you want the footnote number to appear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;input&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;checkbox&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;cb1&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;label&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;for=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;cb1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;This is the footnote text.&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is the CSS code with comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-markdown highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/&lt;span class=&quot;ge&quot;&gt;* This initially hides the footnote (i.e. span)  *&lt;/span&gt;/
input&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;type=checkbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; ~ span {
    display:none; 
}

/&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; This styles the footnote text which appears 
when the label is clicked  &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
input&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;type=checkbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;:checked ~ span {
    display:inline; 
    font-size: 85%;
    font-family:$monospace;
    color: mix(#000, $text-color, 30%);
    cursor:default;
}

/&lt;span class=&quot;ge&quot;&gt;* This permanently hides the checkbox  *&lt;/span&gt;/
input&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;type=checkbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;{
    display:none;  
}

/&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; This styles the footnote label to appear 
like a hyperlink  &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
input&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;type=checkbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; ~ label {
    display:inline;
    cursor:pointer;
    color:$link-color;
    text-decoration:underline;
}

/&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; This styles the footnote label when the mouse 
hover over it &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
input&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;type=checkbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; ~ label:hover {
    text-decoration:underline;
    cursor:pointer;
    color:red;
}

/&lt;span class=&quot;ge&quot;&gt;* This styles the footnote label after it is clicked *&lt;/span&gt;/
input&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;type=checkbox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;:checked ~ label {
    color:red;
    text-decoration:none;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the Jekyll theme called Minimal Mistakes like I am, you can learn how to update the style sheet &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/docs/stylesheets/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; in the official Docs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Stevans</name><email>stevans@utexas.edu</email></author><summary type="html">Click here to jump to the section with the code.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using US Census APIs to investigate the drop in youth-voter turnout in 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/youth-vote/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using US Census APIs to investigate the drop in youth-voter turnout in 2020" /><published>2020-04-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/youth-vote</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/youth-vote/">&lt;p&gt;After Super Tuesday, young voters were frequently scapegoated by media outlets for Bernie Sanders’s loses in Super Tuesday contests like in this US Today &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/elections/2020/03/04/super-tuesday-bernie-sanders-youth-votes-fell-short-compared-2016/4947795002/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; entitled, &lt;em&gt;Many young voters sat out Super Tuesday, contributing to Bernie Sanders’ losses&lt;/em&gt;. Their reasoning was that a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2020/02/this-one-chart-explains-why-young-voters-back-bernie-sanders.html&quot;&gt;polling&lt;/a&gt; before Super Tuesday showed Sanders with a large support gap, being strongly favored by younger voters and strongly disfavored by older voters. So, for Bernie to have lost, young people must not have made it to the polls. At first glance, exit (and entrance) polling from CNN seems to support this notion. The percentage of voters aged 18 to 29 years old in states that voted on or before March 10th in both &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/election/2016/primaries/polls/&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/entrance-and-exit-polls/&quot;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt; are displayed in the following table. We see that youth voters made up a smaller percentage of 2020 voters in 13 of the 15 states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Youth voter turnout in Democratic Primaries has dropped in terms of percentages&quot; aria-label=&quot;Table&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-xoMeU&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/xoMeU/2/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;background: #FFFFFF; width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;774&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var e in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var t=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-&quot;+e)||document.querySelector(&quot;iframe[src*='&quot;+e+&quot;']&quot;);t&amp;&amp;(t.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][e]+&quot;px&quot;)}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!--- &lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/youth-vote/youth_voter_turnout_wtitle.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: ;&quot;
       alt=&quot;Three column table showing youth voter turnout in 2016 and 2020 and the difference.&quot;&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Voter Turnout for 18-29 year-olds in Democratic Presidential Primaries. Sources: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/election/2016/primaries/polls/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/entrance-and-exit-polls/&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
 ---&gt;

&lt;!--- &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/youth_vote_post/youth_voter_turnout_wtitle.png&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/youth_vote_post/youth_voter_turnout_wtitle.png&quot; caption=&quot;Voter Turnout for 18-29 year-olds in Democratic Presidential Primaries. Sources: [[1]](https://www.cnn.com/election/2016/primaries/polls/) [[2]](https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/entrance-and-exit-polls/)&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ---&gt;

&lt;!--- &lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/youth_vote_post/youth_voter_turnout_wtitle.png&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 5em; margin-right: 5em; max-width: 200px;&quot;
       alt=&quot;Three column table showing youth voter turnout in 2016 and 2020 and the difference.&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Voter Turnout for 18-29 year-olds in Democratic Presidential Primaries. Sources: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/election/2016/primaries/polls/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/entrance-and-exit-polls/&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt; ---&gt;

&lt;!--- While the margin of error of exit polls is typically 3-4%, averages are more robust. The average difference in youth voter turnout in these 15 states is -2.4%. Weighted by the number of 2020 voters in each state, the weighted average is even larger, -2.8%. ---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, when you consider the total number of young voters who cast votes in these 15 contests, you see that more young voters voted this year than 4 years ago. For example, in Texas the youth turn out went down 5% but the total number of youth voters increased by about 25,000. So how can both changes be true? Of course, it means that older voters had a larger increase in number (and percentage) than youth voters in 2020. This made me wonder, could this be explained simply by the fact that the US population is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/newsroom/blogs/random-samplings/2016/06/americas-age-profile-told-through-population-pyramids.html&quot;&gt;aging&lt;/a&gt;, if all else is held equal to 2016? Or, has the propensity to vote of older voters change, too? And, how will projected demographic changes effect electorate compositions in future elections?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin to answer these questions, I turned to the Census Bureau, which has estimated the population of the US since it was founded in 1902 and published their population estimates &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;. I was able to scrape together the US population broken down by single year of age since the year 1900. Given that the data was collected at various times over more than a century, the data isn’t perfectly homogenous in structure. For example, the only available data from 1900-1929 exclude Armed Forces overseas and the population residing in Alaska and Hawaii, the 1930-1959 numbers include Armed Forces overseas but exclude the population residing in Alaska and Hawaii, and the 2010s data has the most granular demographic breakdowns of the population of all decades (down to metropolitan division scales). I decided to use the data that include Armed Forces overseas in this analysis when available because, in principle, the Armed Forces could vote (although, in practice, I suspect it has been difficult to impossible). Methods for accessing the data vary, too; from excel spreadsheets on a webpage, like for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/data/tables/time-series/demo/popest/pre-1980-national.html&quot;&gt;1900-1979&lt;/a&gt;, to an array of Census Population Estimates &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/data/developers/data-sets/popest-popproj/popest.html&quot;&gt;APIs&lt;/a&gt; for years 1990 to 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--primary&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check it out!&lt;/strong&gt; The python code I used to corral and clean the data can be found in a Jupyter Notebook on my GitHub page &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/stevans/youth-voters-census-data/blob/master/notebooks/Exploring_census_data.ipynb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the US population per single year of age in every year from 1900 to 2020 (and projected out to 2060), I was able to calculate and plot the fraction of the population that falls in the category of youth voter (aged 18-29).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/youth-vote/youth_fraction.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: ;&quot; alt=&quot;Plot of the fraction of the US population aged 18-29 from 1900-2060.&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Fraction of the US population aged 18-29 years old.

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To first order, the most obvious feature of this plot is the general trend downwards from 37% in 1900 to 21% in 2020. The next most significant feature is the large bump from about 1965 to 1995, when the Baby Boomer generation aged into and then out of the 18-29 age range. Also noticeable in the figure is a relatively small dip around 1918, when more than 4 million (mostly young) service people were overseas fighting in WWI. This is the only wartime period associated with such a dip in the figure because the census population worksheets I found include the population of Armed Forces overseas after 1940.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1972, when the major parties officially tied their convention delegates to the outcomes of state primaries, the fraction of the population comprised of 18-29 year-olds has decreased from 29% to 21%. This means that young people were outnumbered by all other voters ~2:1 in 1970 and are outnumbered by ~4:1 today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-the-aging-us-population-explain-the-drop-in-youth-voter-turnout-between-2016-and-2020-alone&quot;&gt;Can the aging US population explain the drop in youth voter turnout between 2016 and 2020 alone?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer is, “No.” I found the population aged 18-29 has shrunk by ~266,000 from March 3, 2016 to Mar 3, 2020 (by interpolating the yearly Census data) and the 30-and-over population has grown by ~8,774,000 in the same timespan. In terms of the youth voter fraction of the electorate, this results in a decrease of ~0.7% from 21.6% on Super Tuesday in 2016 (March 1) to 20.9% in on Super Tuesday in 2016 (March 3). Furthermore, if all voter demographic groups voted at the same rates as in 2016 (historical voting rate estimates from the Census Bureau were found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/data/tables/time-series/demo/voting-and-registration/voting-historical-time-series.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), the youth turnout would appear to decrease by only ~0.5% in 2020 simply due to changes in the population age distribution. Since this is less than the 2.8% drop in the median youth voter turnout seen in 2020 exit polling compared to 2016, something in addition to age distribution change is needed to fully explain how the youth voter turnout could decrease in percentages while increase in total numbers. As mentioned earlier, the simple explanation is that older voters voted at a higher rate than they had four years ago. This seems very likely to me, as I suspect it is easy for the ~70% of the oldest population that votes to recruit a few percent of their cohort to join them at the polls than it is for the voting ~30-40% of 18-29-year-olds to get an equivalent number of their peers to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-will-projected-demographic-changes-effect-electorate-compositions-in-future-elections&quot;&gt;How will projected demographic changes effect electorate compositions in future elections?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the youth fraction plot at years after 2020, we see a steady decline to about 17% in 2060. That’s 4.6% less than it is today. This suggests that all future presidential campaign relying on the youth vote will have an even taller task than Bernie had in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Stevans</name><email>stevans@utexas.edu</email></author><summary type="html">After Super Tuesday, young voters were frequently scapegoated by media outlets for Bernie Sanders’s loses in Super Tuesday contests like in this US Today article entitled, Many young voters sat out Super Tuesday, contributing to Bernie Sanders’ losses. Their reasoning was that a lot of polling before Super Tuesday showed Sanders with a large support gap, being strongly favored by younger voters and strongly disfavored by older voters. So, for Bernie to have lost, young people must not have made it to the polls. At first glance, exit (and entrance) polling from CNN seems to support this notion. The percentage of voters aged 18 to 29 years old in states that voted on or before March 10th in both 2016 and 2020 are displayed in the following table. We see that youth voters made up a smaller percentage of 2020 voters in 13 of the 15 states.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does the wavelength of a photon change during its travel through intergalactic space?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/energy-of-photons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does the wavelength of a photon change during its travel through intergalactic space?" /><published>2020-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/energy-of-photons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/energy-of-photons/">&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;This is a post I wrote back in 2015 for &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.askanastronomer.org&quot;&gt;AskAnAstronomer.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, a website where astrnonomers answer user-submitted space-related questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is George’s question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When I took physics in college, I seem to remember a formula that related the wavelength of light to its energy. Could the wavelength of a photon of light be altered by a loss of energy, however small, over its path through intergalactic space?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If that were true, looking at a trip of millions / billions of light years… wouldn’t that have some effect on our measurements of redshift, distances, and the expansion rate of the universe?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to your first question is yes, for all intents and purposes, photons traveling through intergalactic space could, and in fact do, lose energy due to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metric_expansion_of_space&quot;&gt;expansion of spacetime&lt;/a&gt; in the Universe. As the photons lose energy their wavelengths become longer. As you recall, there is a formula that relates a photon’s energy to its wavelength: E = h*c/lambda, or in words, the energy of photon equals Planck’s constant times the speed of light divided by the photon’s wavelength. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photon_energy&quot;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; for a more detailed discussion of this equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for your second question (Does this effect impact our measurements of redshifts, distances, and the expansion of the universe?), in principle, yes it has an impact, but in practice, even if it’s not taken into account, the impact is very small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In astronomy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redshift&quot;&gt;redshift&lt;/a&gt; measurements are actually the measurement of the energy lost by photons emitted from a distance source due to the expansion of the universe. Astronomers measure this loss of energy by, for example, measuring the shift in the wavelength of spectral lines in galaxy spectra. They are called “redshifts” because the spectral lines of distant galaxies are always shifted to longer wavelengths or to the “red”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for measurements of distances, astronomers use many &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_distance_ladder&quot;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to measure distances which are affected by photon “energy loss” to a varying degree. Some methods like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallax&quot;&gt;parallax technique&lt;/a&gt; do not depend on the energy of photons at all and other methods depend on the energy of photons to a large degree like using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cepheid_variable&quot;&gt;Cepheid variable stars&lt;/a&gt; and their period-luminosity relation or using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_distance_ladder#Type_Ia_light_curves&quot;&gt;light curves of Type Ia supernovae&lt;/a&gt;. But even for the latter methods the effect of photon “energy-loss” on the distance measurement is about one percent or less, while other factors effect the distance measurement to a larger extent. These other factors include: light contamination (or blending) from other stars, the varying extinction (or dimming) effect of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_distance_ladder#Classical_Cepheids&quot;&gt;dust near the Cepheid&lt;/a&gt;, and/or the uncertainty in our models of how Cepheid variable stars and supernovae work. These effects result in distance measurements that are uncertain by 5-17%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in conclusion, photons can lose energy while traveling through space, astronomers measure this loss of energy by measuring redshifts, and our measurements of distance (and therefore &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubble%27s_law&quot;&gt;the expansion of the universe&lt;/a&gt;) are impacted by this effect but only slightly and if it’s not taken into account by the astronomers doing the measuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regards,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt Stevans&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;UT Austin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Stevans</name></author><summary type="html">This is a post I wrote back in 2015 for AskAnAstronomer.org, a website where astrnonomers answer user-submitted space-related questions.</summary></entry></feed>